Welcome back. I will take few pieces of code and show you how to analyse them, how to find out the time complexity for them.
다시 돌아오신 것을 환영합니다. 몇 가지 코드 조각을 가져와서 분석하는 방법과 시간 복잡도를 찾는 방법을 보여드리겠습니다.
This is a simple loop. I am not writing a complete algorithm. I have just written a piece of code in which one statement is there.
이것은 간단한 반복문입니다. 전체 알고리즘을 작성하는 것이 아니라, 하나의 문장이 있는 코드 조각을 작성했습니다.
Now we are already familiar with this one. We know that this will execute for n plus 1 time.
이제 우리는 이것에 익숙합니다. 이것이 n 플러스 1번 실행된다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
And this will execute for n time. We don't want this time.
그리고 이것은 n번 실행됩니다. 우리는 이 시간을 원하지 않습니다.
Because anyway when we are writing order of, we are writing a degree.
왜냐하면 어쨌든 차수를 쓸 때, 우리는 차수를 쓰고 있기 때문입니다.
So this will not affect the degree at all. So it will be same only.
그래서 이것은 차수에 전혀 영향을 미치지 않습니다. 그래서 동일하게 유지됩니다.
So just we need to know the statement how many times it is executing.
그래서 우리는 문장이 몇 번 실행되는지만 알면 됩니다.
So that's it. So this is order of n.
그게 전부입니다. 그래서 이것은 n의 차수입니다.
You can avoid this one. Skip this one.
이것은 피할 수 있습니다. 이것을 건너뛰세요.
Next.
다음.
If suppose this loop is starting from n and the condition is greater than 1 or 0 and this is getting subtracted.
만약 이 반복문이 n에서 시작하고 조건이 1 또는 0보다 크며 이것이 감소하고 있다면,
So this loop is decrementing.
이 반복문은 감소하고 있는 것입니다.
Then also this statement will execute for n times.
그렇다면 이 문장도 n번 실행됩니다.
And it's order of n.
그리고 이것은 n의 차수입니다.
Whether you go from 1 to 10, 10 steps or come from 10 to 1, then also 10 steps.
1에서 10까지 가든, 10단계든, 10에서 1로 오든, 10단계입니다.
So you go from 1 to 10 or 10 to 1. Same number of steps.
그래서 1에서 10으로 가든 10에서 1로 오든, 같은 단계 수입니다.
So that's how n to 0 it is. So it's also order of n.
그래서 n에서 0으로 가는 것입니다. 그래서 이것도 n의 차수입니다.
If this is starting from 1 and condition is less than n and i is being incremented by 2.
만약 이것이 1에서 시작하고 조건이 n보다 작으며 i가 2씩 증가한다면,
So this statement will not repeat for n times but half of the n times.
이 문장은 n번 반복되지 않고 n의 절반만큼 반복됩니다.
n by 2.
n 나누기 2입니다.
If it is n by 2 also, if I say function is n by 2, what is the degree of polynomial?
만약 n 나누기 2라면, 함수가 n 나누기 2라고 할 때, 다항식의 차수는 무엇입니까?
n only. So it's order of n again.
n입니다. 그래서 이것도 n의 차수입니다.
So in this case also it's order of n.
이 경우에도 n의 차수입니다.
Even if it is incrementing by 20, then this is 20.
심지어 20씩 증가하더라도, 이것은 20입니다.
Degree of a polynomial is n. So this is also order of n.
다항식의 차수는 n입니다. 그래서 이것도 n의 차수입니다.
So n by anything, whatever the number of times it is incrementing, the time will be same.
그래서 n 나누기 무엇이든, 증가하는 횟수가 무엇이든, 시간은 동일합니다.
Next.
다음.
We are already familiar with this one.
우리는 이것에 이미 익숙합니다.
These are two loops, nested loop, one inside another.
이것들은 두 개의 반복문, 중첩된 반복문입니다. 하나가 다른 하나 안에 있습니다.
And this we know this will execute for n times.
그리고 이것은 n번 실행된다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
So this is also n times and this is also n times.
그래서 이것도 n번이고 이것도 n번입니다.
Actually it's n plus 1.
사실은 n 플러스 1입니다.
But what about this one? Again this will repeat for n plus 1 times and this will repeat for n times.
하지만 이건 어떨까요? 이것도 n 플러스 1번 반복되고, 이건 n번 반복됩니다.
And this is order of n square.
그리고 이것은 n 제곱의 순서입니다.
The next is again nested for loop.
다음은 다시 중첩된 for 루프입니다.
This looks similar to the previous one but not.
이것은 이전 것과 비슷해 보이지만 그렇지 않습니다.
See, i takes value 0, i less than n.
보세요, i는 0부터 n보다 작습니다.
But j takes value j less than i.
하지만 j는 i보다 작습니다.
So here is the difference.
여기 차이가 있습니다.
So let us analyse this by tracing this one and find out how much time it is taking.
그래서 이것을 추적하여 얼마나 시간이 걸리는지 분석해 봅시다.
So for this, I will take i value and j value and trace them.
그래서 이를 위해 i 값과 j 값을 추적하겠습니다.
Let us start.
시작해 봅시다.
Initially i is 0.
처음에 i는 0입니다.
When i is 0, j starts from 0 and 0 less than 0?
i가 0일 때, j는 0부터 시작하고 0이 0보다 작나요?
No, it will not execute for any number of times.
아니요, 한 번도 실행되지 않습니다.
So here I have to find out how many times this statement is executed.
그래서 이 문장이 몇 번 실행되는지 찾아야 합니다.
So number of times.
그래서 실행 횟수입니다.
So it will not execute at all, so 0 times.
전혀 실행되지 않으므로 0번입니다.
Then this loop ends.
그럼 이 루프가 끝납니다.
Again, i plus plus.
다시, i 플러스 플러스.
i becomes 1.
i는 1이 됩니다.
i is less than n, suppose.
i는 n보다 작다고 가정합시다.
It is entered inside.
안으로 들어갑니다.
Then again this loop.
다시 이 루프입니다.
0.
0.
0 is less than i.
0은 i보다 작습니다.
Yes, for 0 it will execute.
네, 0일 때 실행됩니다.
Then j plus plus.
그 다음 j 플러스 플러스.
j is 1.
j는 1입니다.
1 is not less than i.
1은 i보다 작지 않습니다.
So for 1, it will not execute.
그래서 1일 때는 실행되지 않습니다.
So how many times it has executed?
그래서 몇 번 실행되었나요?
One time.
한 번입니다.
Then goes up again.
그 다음 다시 올라갑니다.
i plus plus.
i 플러스 플러스.
i becomes 2.
i는 2가 됩니다.
Then j will execute for 0, 1.
그 다음 j는 0, 1에서 실행됩니다.
And when it becomes 2, it will stop.
그리고 2가 되면 멈춥니다.
So this will repeat for 2 times.
그래서 이건 2번 반복됩니다.
And when i is 3, j will take 0, 1, 2 and 3.
그리고 i가 3일 때, j는 0, 1, 2, 3을 가집니다.
So this will repeat for 3 times.
그래서 이건 3번 반복됩니다.
And this process continues.
그리고 이 과정은 계속됩니다.
See, when i was 0, it was never executed.
보세요, i가 0일 때는 실행되지 않았습니다.
When i was 1, it was executed for one time.
i가 1일 때는 한 번 실행되었습니다.
This is a statement.
이것이 문장입니다.
i was 2, it was executed for 2 times, 3, 3 times, so on.
i가 2일 때는 2번, 3일 때는 3번, 계속해서.
So on.
계속해서.
Up to what?
어디까지?
n.
n까지.
So total, when it is n, how many times this will execute?
그래서 총, n일 때, 몇 번 실행될까요?
n times.
n번입니다.
When i was 3, so 3 times.
i가 3일 때, 그래서 3번입니다.
So if it is reaching till n, actually it is less than n, but let us say n.
그래서 n까지 도달하면, 실제로는 n보다 작지만, n이라고 합시다.
It is reaching till n, so it will execute for 10 times.
n까지 도달하면, 10번 실행됩니다.
So total how many times it has executed?
그래서 총 몇 번 실행되었나요?
This one.
이것입니다.
Right?
맞죠?
So I am assuming that it is going till n, though it is not till n.
그래서 n까지 간다고 가정합니다, 실제로는 n까지는 아닙니다.
It is less than n.
n보다 작습니다.
How many times?
몇 번인가요?
1 plus 2 plus 3 plus goes on to n.
1 더하기 2 더하기 3 더하기 계속해서 n까지.
This is nothing but n into n plus 1 by 2.
이것은 n 곱하기 n 더하기 1 나누기 2와 같습니다.
What is the degree of this one?
이것의 차수는 무엇인가요?
f of n is n squared plus 1 by 2, degrees squared.
f(n)은 n 제곱 더하기 1 나누기 2, 차수는 제곱입니다.
So order of n squared.
그래서 n 제곱의 차수입니다.
So the time complexity is order of n squared.
그래서 시간 복잡도는 n 제곱의 차수입니다.
Though this is not similar to the previous one, but if you analyze, the answer is coming
이것이 이전 것과 비슷하지 않지만, 분석해보면 답은
to n squared only.
n 제곱으로 나옵니다.
The degree of a polynomial is n squared only.
다항식의 차수는 n 제곱입니다.
Next code is, here p is initialized to 0, and there is a loop that is not going
다음 코드는 여기서 p가 0으로 초기화되고, 루프가 n번 실행되지 않습니다.
to execute for n times.
이 p를 보세요.
See this p.
p는 n 이하입니다.
p is less than equal to n.
i가 n 이하가 아닙니다.
It is not i less than equal to n.
그래서 조건이 다릅니다.
So the condition is different.
그럼 p는 무엇인가요?
Then what is p?
p는 처음에 0이고 매번 i가 p에 더해집니다.
So now we don't know how many times it is going to execute.
그래서 몇 번 실행될지 모릅니다.
Let us analyze.
분석해봅시다.
I will take i value and p value.
i 값과 p 값을 가져오겠습니다.
Initially this is 0 and this is 1.
처음에는 0이고 이것은 1입니다.
So what happens first time?
첫 번째로 무슨 일이 일어나나요?
This 1 is added and it becomes 1.
이 1이 더해져서 1이 됩니다.
The next time it will be 2.
다음에는 2가 됩니다.
So it will be 1 plus 2.
그래서 1 더하기 2가 됩니다.
So it will be 3.
그래서 3이 됩니다.
The next time, i will be 3 and this will be 1 plus 2 plus 3.
다음에는 i가 3이 되고 이것은 1 더하기 2 더하기 3이 됩니다.
Then i will be 4, it will be 1 plus 2 plus 3 plus 4 goes on.
그 다음 i가 4가 되면 1 더하기 2 더하기 3 더하기 4가 계속됩니다.
How many times it is going to execute?
몇 번 실행될까요?
It is going to execute for k times.
k번 실행될 것입니다.
So what this will be?
그래서 이게 뭐가 될까요?
1 plus 2 plus 3 plus 4 plus goes on to k times.
1 더하기 2 더하기 3 더하기 4 더하기 계속해서 k번까지.
Why i wrote k here?
왜 여기 k를 썼을까요?
It is not reaching, it is not repeating for n times.
n번 반복되는 게 아니기 때문입니다.
Definitely it is repeating for some number of times that we don't know.
확실히 몇 번 반복되는지는 모르지만 반복됩니다.
We are sure that it will not execute for n times.
n번 실행되지 않는다는 것은 확실합니다.
Then how many times?
그럼 몇 번일까요?
Because the condition is different.
조건이 다르기 때문입니다.
So i said let it be k and let us find out that k.
그래서 k라고 하고 그 k를 찾아봅시다.
So if it is repeating for k times, then what is the condition?
k번 반복된다면 조건은 무엇일까요?
We assume that p has become greater than n.
p가 n보다 커졌다고 가정합니다.
So when p became greater than n, it is stopping.
그래서 p가 n보다 커지면 멈춥니다.
We assume this.
이렇게 가정합니다.
As long as p is less than n, but when it is repeating, so when p becomes greater than n, it is stopping.
p가 n보다 작은 동안 반복되다가, p가 n보다 커지면 멈춥니다.
Since p is what?
p는 무엇일까요?
Cp, it is k into k plus 1 by 2.
Cp, 즉 k 곱하기 k 더하기 1 나누기 2입니다.
p is k into k plus 1 by 2.
p는 k 곱하기 k 더하기 1 나누기 2입니다.
So what is the condition?
그럼 조건은 무엇일까요?
k into k plus 1 by 2 is greater than n.
k 곱하기 k 더하기 1 나누기 2가 n보다 큽니다.
So when it will stop, when k into k plus 1 by 2 has become greater than n, it will stop.
그래서 k 곱하기 k 더하기 1 나누기 2가 n보다 커지면 멈춥니다.
So what is k?
그럼 k는 무엇일까요?
Roughly we assume it as k squared.
대략적으로 k 제곱이라고 가정합니다.
k is root n.
k는 루트 n입니다.
So this loop will execute for order of root n times.
그래서 이 루프는 루트 n번 실행됩니다.
Let me show you quickly.
빠르게 보여드리겠습니다.
i is sign 1.
i는 1입니다.
i p is less than equal to n.
i p는 n보다 작거나 같습니다.
i plus plus.
i 증가.
This is not i less than equal to n.
이것은 i가 n보다 작거나 같은 것이 아닙니다.
So we don't know how many times it is repeating.
그래서 몇 번 반복되는지 알 수 없습니다.
i is here, p is here.
i는 여기 있고, p는 여기 있습니다.
So i values are incrementing and every time i is added to p.
그래서 i 값이 증가하고 매번 i가 p에 더해집니다.
So we don't know how many times.
그래서 몇 번인지 알 수 없습니다.
So let us say k times.
그래서 k번이라고 해봅시다.
And this will be 1 plus 2 plus 2 to k.
그리고 이것은 1 더하기 2 더하기 2부터 k까지입니다.
Right?
맞죠?
So that k is p is k into k plus 1 by 2 now.
그래서 k는 p가 k 곱하기 k 더하기 1 나누기 2입니다.
So we know that this will repeat as long as p is less than equal to n.
그래서 p가 n보다 작거나 같은 동안 반복된다는 것을 압니다.
So it will stop when p becomes greater than n.
그래서 p가 n보다 커지면 멈춥니다.
So when p becomes greater than n, it will stop.
p가 n보다 커지면 멈춥니다.
So k into k plus 1 by 2 becomes greater than n.
그래서 k 곱하기 k 더하기 1 나누기 2가 n보다 커지면 멈춥니다.
It will stop.
멈출 것입니다.
So this is k squared and k is root n.
그래서 이것은 k 제곱이고 k는 루트 n입니다.
In the next video you will find more examples.
다음 비디오에서 더 많은 예제를 찾을 수 있습니다.
So different type of codes.
그래서 다양한 유형의 코드들입니다.
I will show you and i will show you how to analyze them.
제가 보여드리고 분석하는 방법을 보여드리겠습니다.
So this is how by tracing you can analyze them.
그래서 이렇게 추적하여 분석할 수 있습니다.
So in the other video, next video also you can find few more algorithms with tracing.
다른 비디오, 다음 비디오에서도 추적과 함께 몇 가지 알고리즘을 찾을 수 있습니다.